A Guide to the Friends of Dyke Marsh Records, 1948-2019
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Friends of Dyke Marsh Records, 1948-2019
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-72
6 linear feet
The Friends of Dyke Marsh Records consists of 6.0 linear feet and span the years 1948 to 2019 and consists of correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, and promotional materials. Subjects covered are the history of Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve and FODM, and scientific studies and the conservation of Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve.
Friends of Dyke Marsh
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Friends of Dyke Marsh though Dorothy McManus on July 9, 2019.
Historical and Biographical Information
The Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve is a freshwater tidal marsh located in Fairfax County on the Potomac River, just south of Alexandria, Virginia, and is administered by the National Park Service (NPS) as part of George Washington Memorial Parkway. The Friends of Dyke Marsh (FODM) is a volunteer group dedicated to preserving, protecting, and restoring the Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve through education, science, and stewardship.
FODM was formed in 1975 by a group of local citizens who wanted to stop plans to use the marsh as a dumping ground for dredged river spoil. The group formally organized as a non-profit organization in order to cooperate with the National Park Service and was incorporated in 1976. Their efforts include: holding quarterly meetings and other programs open to the public, publishing a newsletter called The Marsh Wren, raising money to sponsor scientific studies of the marsh, conducting nature walks and surveys, hosting trash clean-ups, preparing informational materials, encouraging public stewardship, and helping NPS control invasive plants.
Scope and Content
The Friends of Dyke Marsh Records consists of 6.0 linear feet and span the years 1948 to 2019 and consists of correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, and promotional materials. Subjects covered are the history of Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve and FODM, and scientific studies and the conservation of Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve.
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1955-2018, Undated Boxes 1-3
Arranged alphabetically by subject. This series contains by-laws of Friends of Dyke Marsh, laws and regulations related to Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve, history of Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve and Friends of Dyke Marsh, membership information, fundraising documents, tax documents, awards, materials related to anniversaries of Friends of Dyke Marsh, photographs, and promotional materials.
Series 2: Meeting Minutes, 1989-2018, Boxes 3-5
Arranged chronologically. This series contains meeting minutes from meetings held by Friends of Dyke Marsh from 1989 to 2018.
Series 3: Newsletters, 1988-2019, Box 6
Arranged chronologically. This series contains newsletters published by Friends of Dyke Marsh, entitled The Marsh Wren, from 1988 to 2019.
Series 4: Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1948-2019, Undated, Box 7
Arranged chronologically. This series contains newspaper clippings and published articles related to Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve and Friends of Dyke Marsh from 1948 to 2019.
Series 5: Studies and Reports, 1963-2013, Undated, Boxes 8-10
Arranged chronologically. This series contains studies and reports that were carried out in Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve and other related studies from 1963 to 2013. Also included is correspondence between Friends of Dyke Marsh, the National Park Service, scientists, and others regarding the studies.
Series 6: Advocacy, 1976-2018, Undated, Boxes 11-12
Arranged alphabetically by subject. This series contains correspondence, reports, and documents related to specific advocacy issues in Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve from 1976 to 2018. Subjects include Belle Haven Marina, boardwalk construction, commercial fishing, hunting, hydrilla control, National Harbor, restoration of Dyke Marsh, and Woodrow Wilson Bridge.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve (Va.); Friends of Dyke Marsh; Marshes - Virginia; National parks and reserves; United States - National Park Service; Wetlands - Virginia; Wildlife conservation - Virginia - Fairfax County; Wildlife refuges - Virginia
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 1955-2018, Undated
  - 30th Anniversary of Friends of Dyke Marsh [Invitation], 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 40th Anniversary of Friends of Dyke Marsh [Invitation and News Article], 2016 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 50th Anniversary of Friends of Dyke Marsh [Correspondence and Planning], 2009 March - October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 50th Anniversary of Friends of Dyke Marsh [Invitation, Photo, Remarks, News Article], 2009 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards, 1988, 1991, 2010, 2014, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Award - 2010 Mount Vernon District Organization of the Year Award [Plaque and Commendation], 2010 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles of Incorporation of Friends of Dyke Marsh, 1989-2014 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - By-Laws, 1987-2015 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Calendar Featuring Dyke Marsh [Buke and Herbert Bank], 2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Related to Meetings and Events, 1990, 1996-1997, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Congressman John Dingell, 2001, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Friends of Dyke Marsh PowerPoint Presentation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Friends of Dyke Marsh Webpage and CD wth JPG, 1997, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fundraising - Grant Application and WETA Drive, 1990, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fundraising - WUSA News Announcement of Grant to Dyke Marsh [DVD], 2013 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Historical Maps of Areas Surrounding Dyke Marsh, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Historical Maps of Dyke Marsh Boundaries, Umdated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - History of Dyke Marsh and Friends of Dyke Marsh, 2001, 2006, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Jackson Abbott - Correspondence and Publications Regarding Jackson Abbott and Memorial, 1983-2007 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Laws - Act Establishing the National Park Service and Laws Relating to George Washington Memorial Parkway, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Laws - Public Law 86-41 - Correspondence Related to the Transfer of Land to the National Park Service, 1955, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Laws - Public Law 86-41, To Acquire Land Along Mount Vernon Highway [Act and Congressional Debates], 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Laws - House Resolution 701 and Senate Resolution 297, To Recognize Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Laws - Senate Joint Resolution 190, Commending the Friends of Dyke Marsh, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Laws and Regulations for Areas Administered by the National Park Service, 1983, 1989, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Laws, Regulations, and Policy Related to Dyke Marsh/Belle Haven, George Washington Memorial Parkway, 1992 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Laws and Regulations, National Park Service - Director's Order #21: Donations and Fundraising, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Legal Agreement Between the National Park Service and VA Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Legal Agreement Between the National Park Service and Friends of Dyke Marsh, 1995-2017 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Legal Agreement Regarding Friends of Dyke Marsh Logo, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Legal Decisions Regarding Boundaries of Dyke Marsh, 1928-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Legal Decisions Regarding Hunting Embayment, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Legal Hearing - Hunting Creek Landfill, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Legislative History and Summary of Documents Pertinent to Dyke Marsh, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Legislative History and Intent, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Member Addresses and Dues, 1995-1996, 2002, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - On the Edge: The Potomac River Dyke Marsh by Dave Eckert [Planning and Film Premiere], 2005-2006, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - On the Edge: The Potomac River Dyke Marsh by Dave Eckert [DVD], 2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Dyke Marsh, 1988, 1990, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Broken Boardwalk from Hurricane Isabel, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Dyke Marsh and Recognition from National Park Service, 2006 March 21 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Damage to Dyke Marsh, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Dyke Marsh and Educational Program, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Louis Halle's Trip to Dyke Marsh, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Program for Funeral Services for Members Frank and Anna McKenna, 2013-2014 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Promotional Materials [Brochures, Flyers, Patches, Sticker], 1990-2011, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Restoration of Dyke Marsh Preserve In A Dynamic and Changing World, Presentation by Katia Engelhardt [DVD], 2008 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tax Exemption Application (IRS Form 1023), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Tax Exemption Documents, 1988, 2005-2018 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Meeting Minutes, 1989-2018
  - Meeting Minutes, 1989-2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2001-2004 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2017 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2018 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Newsletters, 1988-2019
  - The Marsh Wren, 1988-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Marsh Wren, 1997-2005 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Marsh Wren, 2006-2011 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Marsh Wren, 2012-2015 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Marsh Wren, 2016-2019 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1948-2019, Undated
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1948-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1983-1989 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1990-1999 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 2000-2004 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 2006-2008 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 2009-2011 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 2012-2013 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 2014-2017 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 2018-2019 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series 5: Studies and Reports, 1963-2013, Undated
  - A List of the Batrachians and Reptiles of the District of Columbia and Vicinity by W.P. Hay [1902, Copy], Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Hydraulic Geometry of A Small Tidal Estuary, USGS, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Observations on the Natural History and Biology of Hunting Creek by F.M. Uhler, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - A Short Natural History of Dyke Marsh by L.K. Thomas, Jr., 1974 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Feasibility Study for Dyke Marsh Demonstration Area [Final Report and Related Correspondence], 1976 November to 1977 January (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Assessment of Dyke Marsh [Draft], National Park Service, 1976 May (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Assessment of Dyke Marsh [Draft], National Park Service, 1977 May (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Environmental Assessment of Dyke Marsh [Final], National Park Service, 1977 June (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - This Was Potomac River by Frederick Tilp [Copy From Book], 1978 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Size and Structure of a South Carolina Salt Marsh Avian Community, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Natural Heritage Resources Inventory of Hunting Bay-Dyke Marsh [Proposal, Progress Report, Final, and Addendum], 1988, 1991-1992, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Fairfax County, Virginia, Tidal Wetlands Mapping Project [Final Report], 1989 February 20 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and Reports Related to Biological Surveys and Monitoring Projects, 1990-1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Draft Dyke Marsh/Belle Haven Management Study and Environmental Assessment [With Related Correspondence], 1990-1995 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Dyke Marsh Bibliography, National Park Service, 1991 March 6 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - A Historical Delineation of the Dyke Marsh Vegetations by Kelso, XU, Marcella, and Thomas [Final Report and Planning], 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Dyke Marsh Herbaceous Plant Study by Dean A. Lindholm, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Visitor Services Project, Belle Haven Park/Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve by Dwight L. Madison, 1994 January (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Feasability Analysis, Belle Haven Marina, 1995 March (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Insect Biodiversity of Dyke Marsh, Edward M. Burrows [Grant Proposal and Planning], 1995-1999 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Survey of Amphibians and Reptiles, 1996-1997, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Dyke Marsh Breeding Bird Survey, 1996, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Tidal Freshwater Marshes and the Need for Their Management by Matthew D. Chua, 1997 July (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Draft Environmental Impact Statement for National Harbor, 1999 February (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - The Dyke Marsh Preserve Ecosystem [Planning, Correspondence, and Publication Documents], 1991-2017 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - The Dyke Marsh Preserve Ecosystem [Draft] by David W. Johnston, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Dyke Marsh Preserve Ecosystem [Edited Draft] by David W. Johnston, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Dyke Marsh Preserve Ecosystem [Published] by David W. Johnston, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Assessment, Raised Boardwalk and Improvements to Wildlife Viewing Areas at Dyke Marsh, National Park Service, 2000 January (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Population Abundance and Habitat Requirements of the Marsh Wren at Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve by Sandy C. Spencer, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Variation in Terrestrial Arthropod and Vascular Plant Diversity in Mid-Atlantic Low Deciduous Forest by Daniel Kjar, 2002 October (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - The History of Ornithology in Virginia by David W. Johnston, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Should We Restore Dyke Marsh? A Management Dilemna Facing George Washington Memorial Parkway, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Belle Haven Watershed Flood Reduction Project, 2008 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Briefing: A Geological Study of Dyke Marsh, George Washington Memorial Parkway, USGS, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Ananlysis of the Deconstruction of Dyke Marsh, George Washington Memorial Parkway, Virginia: Progression, Geologic and Manmade Causes and Effective Restoration Scenarios by Litwin et al, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - A 2011 Inventory of Dragonflies and Damselflies at Dyke Marsh Wildlife Preserve, Fairfax County, Virginia [Final Report], VA Department of Conservation and Recreation, 2013 May (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Series 6: Advocacy Subject Files, 1988-2018, Undated
  - Belle Haven Marina - NPS Concession Agreements, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Belle Haven Marina - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Advocacy Issues at Belle Haven Marina, 1995-1996 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Belle Haven Marina - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Advocacy Issues at Belle Haven Marina, 1997-1998 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Belle Haven Marina - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Advocacy Issues at Belle Haven Marina, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Belle Haven Marina - Newspaper Clippings Regarding Advocacy Issues at Belle Haven Marina, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Belle Haven Marina - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Advocacy Issues at Belle Haven Marina, 2002-2012, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Boardwalk - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Boardwalks in Dyke Marsh, 1983, 1999-2004, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Commercial Fishing - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Commercial Fishing in Dyke Marsh, 1990-1991, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence Related to Various Advocacy Issues, 1976-1989 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Related to Various Advocacy Issues, 1990-1998 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Related to Various Advocacy Issues, 2002-2012, Undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Regarding National Park Service's Legal Obligation to Protect Dyke Marsh, 1990, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Hunting - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Duck and Waterfowl Hunting in Dyke Marsh, 1987-1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Hunting - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Duck and Waterfowl Hunting in Dyke Marsh, 1990, 2008-2010, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Hydrilla - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Regarding Hydrilla Control in the Potomac River, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Hydrilla - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Regarding Hydrilla Control in the Potomac River, 1985, Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - National Harbor - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to Advocacy Issues Regarding National Harbor, 1998-2001, 2008, Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Restoration - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to the Restoration of Dyke Marsh, 2004, 2007, 2012-2014, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Restoration - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to the Restoration of Dyke Marsh, 2017-2018 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Woodrow Wilson Bridge - Correspondence, Reports, and Articles Related to the Woodrow Wilson Bridge Improvement, 1990-1999, Undated (Box 12, Folder 8)